<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>FRidh's blog - Frederik Rietdijk</title><link>https://fridh.nl/</link><description>Discovery consists of seeing what everybody has seen and thinking what nobody has thought -- Albert Szent-Gyorgyi</description><lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><item><title>Finished PhD</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2018/03/11/finished-phd/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Back in September, I
&lt;a href="https://www.chalmers.se/en/departments/ace/calendar/Pages/Frederik-
Rietdijk.aspx"&gt;defended&lt;/a&gt; my PhD thesis. The PDF can be
&lt;a href="http://publications.lib.chalmers.se/records/fulltext/251306/251306.pdf"&gt;found&lt;/a&gt;
in the Chalmers library. Furthermore, I made available a
&lt;a href="https://github.com/FRidh/phd_thesis"&gt;routine&lt;/a&gt; to build the PDF from source,
including the majority of the simulations. This is done using the &lt;a href="https://nixos.org/nix/"&gt;Nix package manager&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 11 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2018-03-11:/2018/03/11/finished-phd/</guid><category>acoustics</category><category>sonorus</category></item><item><title>Urban Sound Planning Symposium</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2016/09/17/urban-sound-planning-symposium/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;On the 15th and 16th of September the &lt;a href="http://www.muellerbbm.com/events/seminars-and-workshops/urban-sound-planning/"&gt;Urban Sound Planning Symposium&lt;/a&gt; took place
at Muller-BBM in Planegg, Germany. This occassion also marked the end of the
SONORUS project. At the symposium we mostly looked back at what we've achieved
these last three years. There was a short poster session and after the event was
over we got our "Urban Sound Planner" certificates. Finally I have something to hang
up next to my shoe-lacing certificate.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2016-09-17:/2016/09/17/urban-sound-planning-symposium/</guid><category>acoustics</category><category>sonorus</category></item><item><title>Research visit to NASA Langley Research Center</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2016/04/07/research-visit-to-nasa-langley-research-center/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In March I was at NASA Langley Research Center in Hampton, Virginia, for a four
week research visit. The goal of the visit was to exchange knowledge on
auralization of aircraft and atmospheric turbulence modeling. During this period
we improved a model I had been working on and demonstrated that this model can
be incorporated in the NASA Auralization Framework (NAF).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was staying with a nice family in the town of Poquoson. While I've grown up
nearby the coast I had never lived this close to the waterside before. I like
the strong wind and smell of salt. It was an interesting experience living in
this part of the United States and quite unlike the places I've lived in so far.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2016-04-07:/2016/04/07/research-visit-to-nasa-langley-research-center/</guid><category>acoustics</category><category>sonorus</category><category>aircraft</category></item><item><title>SONORUS update</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2016/04/06/sonorus-update/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It's been quite a while I've written on this blog about SONORUS, or anything
else in fact. A lot has happened since then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In October and November I was at Chalmers again for 6 weeks, following some
courses. Furthermore, we had the school on Auralization and Visualization as
well as a workshop around the Gothenburg test site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the research visit I attended NixCon in Berlin. NixCon was a conference
about the Nix package manager and the ecosystem around it. Ever since I found
out about Nix it fascinated me. Last summer I began using Nix and in autumn I
switched to NixOS, an operating system entirely managed with Nix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In January we had another SONORUS workshop, this time in Rome. It was my first
time in Rome and I was glad to finally see the Colosseum as well as the
Apostolic Palace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In March I went to the U.S. for a four week research visit to NASA Langley
Research Center. I wrote more about that in another post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And just a couple of days ago we had another workshop, this time in Antwerp, Belgium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The SONORUS project is almost over. In September there will be a final meeting in Munich.
More about that later...&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2016-04-06:/2016/04/06/sonorus-update/</guid><category>acoustics</category><category>sonorus</category></item><item><title>Synthesis of aircraft emission and propagation</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2015/08/21/synthesis-of-aircraft-emission-and-propagation/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a repost of a &lt;a href="https://sonorusfp7.wordpress.com/2015/08/21/synthesis-of-aircraft-emission-and-propagation"&gt;post of mine&lt;/a&gt; at the SONORUS blog&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an earlier post I gave an outline of my project, and mentioned that I am 
currently working on an aircraft emission model for auralization. Since then I 
developed a fully automated method to extract features from aircraft recordings. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The method is roughly as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Backpropagate from source to receiver in time-domain, undoing the Doppler 
shift, atmospheric attenuation and spreading. The ground effect is ignored for 
now. We now have a signal that roughly corresponds to what is emitted from the 
airplane.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Determine fundamental frequency. An aircraft spectrum consists mostly of noise 
and tones, which are mostly harmonics. Knowing the fundamental frequency, allows 
you to determine the power of not only the fundamental, but also of each 
harmonic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And that is the final step. Determine power of the tones, and consider the 
rest of the spectrum as noise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plan is now to determine these features from a large amount of events and 
develop a basic emission model. But before then, its important to already ask 
the following question. Are these features sufficient to create a realistic 
emission signal? Or, even better, are these features, taking into account the 
developed propagation model, providing a realistic signal at the receiver? Does, 
what you hear, really sound like an aircraft? That's in the end what we're 
after, right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Synthesis of emission&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To test whether the obtained features are sufficient to reproduce a realistic 
auralization, I considered a couple of events, and extracted the features for 
each. I synthesized an emission signal by summing all these time-varying 
components (about 200 tones and 30 1/3-octave bands), linearly interpolating the 
samples (features were obtained every second) and smoothing the interpolated 
components.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://zenodo.org/record/28815/files/synthesis.wav"&gt;Click here&lt;/a&gt; to listen 
to a synthesis of the emission. It's an Airbus A320 taking of from Zurich Airport.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first part of the fragment you can hear the tonal components quite clearly 
but in the latter part noise takes over. This is due to the directivity of the 
components; tones generated by the fan blades radiate mostly forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For comparison, &lt;a href="https://zenodo.org/record/28815/files/reverted.wav"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; is the backpropagated signal. You'll notice it sounds very 
different. This is because the (unwanted) ground effect is still in it. And 
because of it, it sounds much more already like an actual aircraft fly-over!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;At the receiver&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, let's listen now at a receiver at a height of 4 meters above the ground. 
When the aircraft is closest by, the distance is about 180 meters. Here are two 
fragments: &lt;a href="https://zenodo.org/record/28815/files/recording.wav"&gt;fragment A&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href="https://zenodo.org/record/28815/files/auralization.wav"&gt;fragment B&lt;/a&gt;. One is a 
full auralization, the other is a recording. Can you hear which is which?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(hint: look at the URL in the top part of your browser if you want to know for sure)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two quite noticeable differences between the recording and the 
auralization. This specific auralization does not include the effects of 
turbulence, and the level of the blade passing frequency is lower than it should 
be.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 21 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2015-08-21:/2015/08/21/synthesis-of-aircraft-emission-and-propagation/</guid><category>acoustics</category><category>sonorus</category><category>urban planning</category><category>aircraft</category></item><item><title>Euronoise slides</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2015/06/04/euronoise-slides/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.18111"&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt; I used for my presentation at Euronoise 2015 can be found online at Zenodo.
The &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15702"&gt;proceedings&lt;/a&gt; are also available.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 04 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2015-06-04:/2015/06/04/euronoise-slides/</guid><category>acoustics</category><category>sonorus</category></item><item><title>Swiss Air Force demonstrations in Duebendorf</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2015/05/19/swiss-air-force-demonstrations-in-duebendorf/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The headquarters of the Swiss Air Force is located in Duebendorf, and the 
airstrip of the base is not that far from where I work. Often you can see 
paratroopers and helicopters or hear other aircraft take off. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Occasionally, one of the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swiss_Air_Force#Air_demonstration_teams"&gt;demonstration teams&lt;/a&gt; practices.
So far I've only seen the PC-7 Team, which use Swiss-manufactered &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pilatus_PC-7"&gt;Pilatus PC-7&lt;/a&gt; turbo prop trainers.
These aircraft can be quite noisy. Actually, it's not that the sound is very loud, it's just that the sound can be 
annoying. The propellors have a strong directivity and therefore, as they do their maneuvers, the level goes up and down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They don't practice that often, and their sessions generally don't last more 
than a couple of hours. Therefore, I can't really be bothered too much by it. 
If I hear them, and it bothers me, I just close my window or turn the music up a 
bit. But what astonishes me is that they actually do these activities above 
dense populated areas. Many people are living and working in the area. What if 
an accident occurs? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realize there aren't many places in Switzerland where they could build 
airstrips and do this kind of training without flying over someone's home. But 
flying over a dense area like this or flying over one or two farms is quite a 
difference. I am curious now to their risk assessment and how they've 
eventually decided to keep doing these activities here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To conclude, these activities can be noisy, and perhaps also dangerous. 
However, on a more positive note, they also provide good entertainment during your break!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2015-05-19:/2015/05/19/swiss-air-force-demonstrations-in-duebendorf/</guid><category>acoustics</category><category>sonorus</category><category>urban planning</category></item><item><title>SONORUS meeting in Naples</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2015/04/29/sonorus-meeting-in-naples/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago there was a &lt;a href="http://fp7sonorus.eu"&gt;SONORUS&lt;/a&gt; meeting and school in Naples and Sorrento, Italy.
The topic of the school was 'Computational Soundscape Analysis'. The next meeting will be in October in Gothenburg, Sweden.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2015-04-29:/2015/04/29/sonorus-meeting-in-naples/</guid><category>acoustics</category><category>work</category><category>sonorus</category></item><item><title>Paper at Euronoise</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2015/04/28/paper-at-euronoise/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.euronoise2015.eu/timetable_tuesday.html"&gt;timetable&lt;/a&gt; for Euronoise 2015 is available. 
I will present the paper &lt;em&gt;Determining an Empirical Emission Model for the Auralization of Jet Aircraft&lt;/em&gt; on Tuesday the second at nine in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seems like my presentation is moved to 10:20.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2015-04-28:/2015/04/28/paper-at-euronoise/</guid><category>acoustics</category><category>work</category><category>sonorus</category></item><item><title>Slides on Zenodo</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2015/03/27/slides-on-zenodo/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;As posted earlier I've been &lt;a href="https://fridh.nl/2014/11/21/posters-and-slides-about-my-project/"&gt;uploading to Zenodo&lt;/a&gt; almost all slides, posters and proceedings that I made during my project.
This includes the &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.16405"&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt; (as well as two auralizations) of the &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1121/1.4900268"&gt;presentation&lt;/a&gt; I gave at the 168th ASA meeting in Indianapolis last year.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2015-03-27:/2015/03/27/slides-on-zenodo/</guid><category>acoustics</category><category>work</category><category>sonorus</category></item><item><title>Research visit to Chalmers</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2015/02/01/research-visit-to-chalmers/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;After the ASA meeting in Indianapolis I went to Gothenburg again for a research 
visit. As I wrote in my previous post it was strange to be there again. Last 
spring I visited Gothenburg for just a couple of days, but now, staying for 
seven weeks again is quite different. You start noticing quite a lot of things 
have changed. Many people I knew there have moved away and I also noticed a 
couple of restaurants I visited have closed since. Despite those things it was nice meeting old friends again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, as I wrote in the title I went there on a research visit. The main reason 
for my visit was to attend some courses at Chalmers but to also work on my 
research. Initially the idea was to investigate further the model we're 
developing to deal with atmospheric turbulence in aircraft auralisations. 
However, in the end the courses took more time then I expected, so I didn't 
really get to work on the turbulence model anymore. However, I did manage to 
implement one nice part of the auralisation tool, namely support for Ambisonics. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides Chalmers I also visited SP in Borås. SP was a familar place for me as 
well since I did an 
&lt;a href="https://fridh.nl/thermoacoustic-refrigerator/"&gt;internship&lt;/a&gt; there in 2010. 
Earlier I had made recordings with a SoundField microphone, however, at Empa we 
do not have an Ambisonics setup. SP has a listening room with a third order 
Ambisonics system, giving me the possibility to listen to the first order 
recording as well as to higher order auralisations. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One visit I met up with Peter Lundén who installed the system. After some problem solving we managed to 
get both the recordings and auralisations working. Unfortunately there was one 
problem with the auralisations, somehow halfway the aircraft makes a U-turn. 
While I haven't checked it any further, I think it is due to 
the inclusion of the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ambisonic_data_exchange_formats#Polarity"&gt;Condon-Shortley phase&lt;/a&gt; 
in the &lt;a href="http://docs.scipy.org/doc/scipy-0.14.0/reference/generated/scipy.special.sph_harm.html"&gt;function&lt;/a&gt; I used to calculate the spherical harmonics.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2015-02-01:/2015/02/01/research-visit-to-chalmers/</guid><category>acoustics</category><category>work</category><category>sonorus</category></item><item><title>168th ASA meeting</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2014/11/21/168th-asa-meeting/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Several weeks ago I was in Indianapolis for the &lt;a href="http://acousticalsociety.org/content/fall-2014-meeting"&gt;168th ASA meeting&lt;/a&gt;. The main reason
for me to go to this conference was to meet fellow &lt;a href="http://vastcon.wordpress.com"&gt;VASTCON&lt;/a&gt; members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conference was quite a bit different from the one I attended in 
&lt;a href="https://fridh.nl/2014/09/14/forum-acusticum-2014-krakow/"&gt;Krakow&lt;/a&gt;. There were spaces 
available that one could work, including internet connectivity, and the chairs 
were actually comfortable. Basically every evening there were activities, 
ranging from a visit to a museum to a Halloween party. While the conference was 
small there were some interesting special sessions, like the session on hot 
topics in acoustics and the session on acoustics and education. From the 
technical sessions I especially liked the session on meta-materials and sonic 
crystals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday morning there was a VASTCON meeting and in the afternoon was the 
VASTCON-organized session on virtual acoustics. During this session I gave a 
presentation on how to include the effects of turbulence on sound propagation 
for auralization of aircraft noise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday me and some others of VASTCON visited the &lt;a href="https://engineering.purdue.edu/Herrick"&gt;Herrick Labs&lt;/a&gt; at Purdue University. There they 
had a very interesting device they used to measure the noise from a rolling 
tyre. The device is basically a circularly shaped road with two wheels on arms 
rotating rapidly moving over the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a (very) short stay in The Netherlands I'm in Gothenburg again at Chalmers.
Strange to be there again!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2014-11-21:/2014/11/21/168th-asa-meeting/</guid></item><item><title>Posters and slides about my project</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2014/11/21/posters-and-slides-about-my-project/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I've &lt;a href="https://zenodo.org/collection/user-sononus"&gt;uploaded&lt;/a&gt; some posters 
and slides about my project to &lt;a href="http://zenodo.org"&gt;ZENODO&lt;/a&gt;.
Back in May I gave a &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.12642"&gt;poster&lt;/a&gt; 
presentation in Eindhoven during our project meeting. In October I presented a 
slightly different &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.12643"&gt;poster&lt;/a&gt; during the Empa PhD symposium.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2014-11-21:/2014/11/21/posters-and-slides-about-my-project/</guid></item><item><title>Publishing data: ZENODO and figshare</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2014/11/21/publishing-data-zenodo-and-figshare/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Searching for a way to publish scientific data I found two interesting 
platforms: &lt;a href="http://figshare.com"&gt;figshare&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://zenodo.org"&gt;ZENODO&lt;/a&gt;.
I've made a &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.12664"&gt;quick comparison&lt;/a&gt; between 
the two platforms. For me the clear winner is ZENODO.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2014-11-21:/2014/11/21/publishing-data-zenodo-and-figshare/</guid></item><item><title>Good Country</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2014/10/09/good-country/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Every other day or so I watch a &lt;a href="http://ted.com"&gt;TED talk&lt;/a&gt; and today I
saw a
&lt;a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/simon_anholt_which_country_does_the_most_good_for_the_world?language=en"&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt;
by Simon Anholt titled &lt;em&gt;Which country does the most good for the
world?&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Policy advisor Simon Anholt thought of a new scale describing how much
good a country does outside its borders, and it's called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://goodcountry.org/"&gt;The Good
Country Index&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. In his talk he discusses why
countries tend to compete instead of cooperate, why this should change
and how this could be changed. He investigated how people perceive other
countries and he found out that the countries we like are the &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt;
countries. Good countries, what do I mean with that you might wonder.
Well, if you want to have an answer on that I suggest watching the talk!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="390"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/1X7fZoDs9KU'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2014-10-09:/2014/10/09/good-country/</guid></item><item><title>mdwiki: a Wiki using Markdown</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2014/10/05/mdwiki-a-wiki-using-markdown/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Some time ago I encountered
&lt;a href="http://dynalon.github.io/mdwiki/#!index.md"&gt;mdwiki&lt;/a&gt;, a Wiki which is
processed entirely client-side. In short:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download &lt;code&gt;mdwiki.html&lt;/code&gt;, put it in the root of your site, and rename
    it to &lt;code&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add &lt;code&gt;index.md&lt;/code&gt; which you use as your index page. Write content in
    your favorite formatting syntax, Markdown :-)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optionally add a
    &lt;a href="http://dynalon.github.io/mdwiki/#!quickstart.md#Adding_a_navigation"&gt;&lt;code&gt;navigation.md&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    for a navigation bar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add any other Markdown file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn't have many features but in my opinion it doesn't have to. It's
great for quickly publishing ideas or content without bothering too much
yet with layout and looks. Now, that doesn't mean it's not possible to
make nice looking sites as can be seen in the
&lt;a href="http://dynalon.github.io/mdwiki/#!examples.md"&gt;examples&lt;/a&gt;. Also, features
can be added using
&lt;a href="http://dynalon.github.io/mdwiki/#!gimmicks.md"&gt;gimmicks&lt;/a&gt;. Examples of
added functionality are the parsing of equations, embedding Google Maps
and YouTube video's.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 05 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2014-10-05:/2014/10/05/mdwiki-a-wiki-using-markdown/</guid></item><item><title>Race Against The Machine</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2014/10/05/race-against-the-machine/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Last year I saw &lt;a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/erik_brynjolfsson_the_key_to_growth_race_em_with_em_the_machines"&gt;this TED talk&lt;/a&gt;
by &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erik_Brynjolfsson"&gt;Erik Brynjolfsson&lt;/a&gt;
on how we should handle the digital revolution. In 2011 he wrote &lt;em&gt;Race
Against the Machine&lt;/em&gt; together with &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew_McAfee"&gt;Andrew McAfee&lt;/a&gt; and last week I
finally got to reading it (okay I admit, I completely forgot it was on
my to read list). It's a good book and I strongly recommend it. The
digital revolution is happening, things are changing and a lot of people
can't keep up with it. Next up, &lt;em&gt;The Second Machine Age&lt;/em&gt;, another book
by Brynjolfsson and McAfee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="390"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/sod-eJBf9Y0'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 05 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2014-10-05:/2014/10/05/race-against-the-machine/</guid></item><item><title>Forum Acusticum 2014, Krakow</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2014/09/14/forum-acusticum-2014-krakow/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Last week the conference &lt;a href="http://fa2014.pl"&gt;Forum Acusticum 2014&lt;/a&gt; took
place in the city of Krakow, Poland. From Monday till Friday there were
presentations as well as meetings of technical committees. The
presentations covered a wide range of topics like structural acoustics,
human response and auralisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A special session was organised on Urban Sound Planning as well, in
which many of my &lt;a href="http://www.fp7sonorus.eu/"&gt;project members&lt;/a&gt; presented
their current work. I'm glad a lot of people attended the session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I gave a presentation with the title &lt;em&gt;Modelling sound propagation in the
presence of turbulence for the auralisation of aircraft noise&lt;/em&gt; in a
session on Environmental Acoustics. This session was Friday morning
early, which was a bit unfortunate, considering there was a nice party
with the &lt;a href="https://www.euracoustics.org/activities/yan"&gt;Young Acousticians Network&lt;/a&gt; the evening
before. I was surprised there were still so many people that morning!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday I joined a discussion on benchmarking for computational
acoustics. When implementing a model you would like to be able to
validate this. This can sometimes be difficult due to lack of available
information or benchmarks. Therefore, the idea is now to put online some
kind of repository where people can put their benchmarks. Considering
this is a topic of interest in other fields of science I am really
curious how they deal with this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The city of Krakow surprised me a lot. It's quite a green city and there
seems to be a good and relaxed mood. There's plenty of pubs and
restaurants, especially around the main square which is huge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, that's my summary on FA2014!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 14 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2014-09-14:/2014/09/14/forum-acusticum-2014-krakow/</guid><category>acoustics</category><category>work</category><category>sonorus</category></item><item><title>Back in Gothenburg for SONORUS</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2014/04/07/back-in-gothenburg-for-sonorus/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Last month I was back in Gothenburg for a week and it was nice! I've
been living in Gothenburg for close to two years and being back there
brought up some good memories. The reason I was there again was that we
had a course for &lt;a href="http://www.fp7sonorus.eu/"&gt;SONORUS&lt;/a&gt; on leadership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the course we treated topics like communication, knowledge, coaching,
group dynamics and decision making. There was one very interesting
exercise on group dynamics. In 20 minutes the entire group had to agree
on a list of statements related to meetings. We also &lt;a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/tom_wujec_build_a_tower"&gt;built a
tower&lt;/a&gt; using dry
spaghetti, a meter of tape and a marshmallow, or at least we tried!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides the course we spent time on some practical matters in the
project, like discussing how we would cooperate, e.g. with regards to
sharing data. Another topic that was discussed is the upcoming
&lt;a href="http://www.chchearing.org/noise-center-home/international-noise-awareness-day"&gt;International Noise Awareness Day&lt;/a&gt;,
but more about that later!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2014-04-07:/2014/04/07/back-in-gothenburg-for-sonorus/</guid><category>acoustics</category><category>sonorus</category></item><item><title>Sparse arrays in Python</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2014/04/07/sparse-arrays-in-python/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Numpy offers dense arrays and both &lt;a href="http://www.numpy.org/"&gt;Numpy&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="http://scipy.org/"&gt;Scipy&lt;/a&gt; offer sparse matrices. However, they don't
offer any sparse array solution. On the web I found some implementations
of sparse arrays but they were generally quite limited:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://launchpad.net/ndsparse"&gt;ndsparse&lt;/a&gt; operators only support
    scalars&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.maths.lth.se/matematiklth/personal/solem/downloads/sparray.py"&gt;sparray&lt;/a&gt;
    operators only support other sparse arrays&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I would like to do is replace in some of my calculations certain
dense arrays with sparse arrays. Numpy compatibility is therefore
important. A first version can be found
&lt;a href="https://github.com/FRidh/sparse"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What works?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The basic operators work with scalars, sparse arrays and dense
    arrays.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic slicing is partially supported. newaxis, None, slice and
    Ellipsis aren't really supported yet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Converting from dense to sparse and vice versa&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What's left to do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finish basic slicing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In-place operators&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advanced slicing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enforcing dtype&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cythonize&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because I was curious I Cythonized it quickly. While it is much much
faster than the plain Python implementation it still is about a factor
1000 slower than dense arrays when operatoring with a dense array.
Unfortunately this is too slow for my use case, so for now I reverted to
using dense arrays but with a reduced model size. Nevertheless I am sure
there is a significant performance increase possible.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2014-04-07:/2014/04/07/sparse-arrays-in-python/</guid><category>python</category></item><item><title>Planet Acoustics</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2014/03/09/planet-acoustics/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I set up a new &lt;a href="http://planetplanet.org"&gt;Planet&lt;/a&gt; aimed at acousticians called 
&lt;a href="http://planetacoustics.org"&gt;Planet Acoustics&lt;/a&gt;. A Planet is basically a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web_syndication"&gt;feed&lt;/a&gt; reader; it downloads news feeds 
published by web sites and aggregates their content together into a single 
combined feed. The purpose of this Planet is to collect blogs and news by and 
for acousticians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Planets are very popular in the open-source software development world. Planets 
like &lt;a href="http://planetkde.org"&gt;Planet KDE&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://planet.debian.org"&gt;Planet Debian&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://planet.python.org"&gt;Planet Python&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://planet.scipy.org"&gt;Planet SciPy&lt;/a&gt; syndicate 
posts from many people all over the world who write posts related to 
respectively &lt;a href="http://kde.org"&gt;KDE&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href="http://debian.org"&gt;Debian&lt;/a&gt; project, &lt;a href="http://python.org"&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt; programming language and the 
Python module &lt;a href="http://scipy.org"&gt;SciPy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The posts on such a Planet give a good overview of which efforts are currently 
taking place. Contrary to news posts, press releases or journal articles they 
are informal. People write about their current work, problems they face, events 
they attend and often share nice tips and tricks or even detailed tutorials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that &lt;a href="http://planetacoustics.org"&gt;Planet Acoustics&lt;/a&gt; will become a Planet with many nice posts regarding acoustics and the life of acousticians.
If you would like to have your posts syndicated, then please send an e-mail to &lt;a href="&amp;#109;&amp;#97;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;&amp;#58;&amp;#97;&amp;#100;&amp;#109;&amp;#105;&amp;#110;&amp;#64;&amp;#112;&amp;#108;&amp;#97;&amp;#110;&amp;#101;&amp;#116;&amp;#97;&amp;#99;&amp;#111;&amp;#117;&amp;#115;&amp;#116;&amp;#105;&amp;#99;&amp;#115;&amp;#46;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;"&gt;&amp;#97;&amp;#100;&amp;#109;&amp;#105;&amp;#110;&amp;#64;&amp;#112;&amp;#108;&amp;#97;&amp;#110;&amp;#101;&amp;#116;&amp;#97;&amp;#99;&amp;#111;&amp;#117;&amp;#115;&amp;#116;&amp;#105;&amp;#99;&amp;#115;&amp;#46;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;&lt;/a&gt; with your name and a link to your &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atom_(standard)"&gt;Atom&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RSS"&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt; feed.
Hopefully, in time, Planet Acoustics will become just as successfull as those Planets I referred to :-)&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2014 19:05:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2014-03-09:/2014/03/09/planet-acoustics/</guid><category>acoustics</category></item><item><title>Blogging with Pelican</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2014/03/09/blogging-with-pelican/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Joining many others I've just switched my blog from Wordpress to Pelican. Writing posts in Markdown or ReStructuredText and no more Wordpress upgrades, yay :-)&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2014 18:20:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2014-03-09:/2014/03/09/blogging-with-pelican/</guid><category>python</category></item><item><title>Modelling a turbulent atmosphere</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2013/12/11/modelling-a-turbulent-atmosphere/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;When listening to an aircraft flying over, you can hear that the level
and spectral contents fluctuate somewhat. These fluctuations are due to
turbulence in the atmosphere, affecting the sound generation (variable
load on engines) and the sound propagation. In order to create a
plausible auralisation of aircraft noise these fluctuations have to be
accounted for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turbulent flow can be modeled as a superposition of a spectrum of
fluctuations and eddies upon a mean flow.&amp;nbsp;A common approach for noise
predictions methods to include the effects of atmospheric turbulence is
to use a statistical approach; generate many random 'frozen' turbulence
fields, calculate for each of these how sound propagates through them
and then average your results. The 'frozen' fields represent snapshots
in time of how the atmosphere could look like. These snapshots are
calculated based on a spectrum of fluctuations. Well known descriptions
of these spectra are the Gaussian and von Karman spectra.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The figure belows shows a portion of two turbulence spectra.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure align-center"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="https://fridh.nl/images/2013/12/Gaussian2DTempWind_and_VonKarman2DTempWind_spectral_density.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://fridh.nl/images/2013/12/Gaussian2DTempWind_and_VonKarman2DTempWind_spectral_density-300x225.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Gaussian and Von Karman spectral densities as function of wavenumber.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A random turbulence field is created by the superposition of modes. The
figure below shows the amplitude of these modes as function of
wavenumber.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure align-center"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="https://fridh.nl/images/2013/12/salomons_figure_J1.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://fridh.nl/images/2013/12/salomons_figure_J1-300x225.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Gaussian and Von Karman mode amplitudes as function of wavenumber.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally a figure showing the refractive-index fluctuation. The field
is generated using a Von Karman spectrum and 200 modes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure align-center"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="https://fridh.nl/images/2013/12/VonKarman2DTempWind_field.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://fridh.nl/images/2013/12/VonKarman2DTempWind_field-300x225.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Von Karmann refractive-index field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2013 10:35:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2013-12-11:/2013/12/11/modelling-a-turbulent-atmosphere/</guid><category>acoustics</category><category>sonorus</category></item><item><title>Lloyd's mirror effect</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2013/11/15/lloyds-mirror-effect/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;When two waves are superimposed on each other it is possible that the
resultant wave has a higher or lower amplitude at certain moments in
time. This phenomenon is called interference. One classical experiment
related to interference is Lloyd's mirror.&amp;nbsp;In the classical experiment,
light from a&amp;nbsp;monochromatic&amp;nbsp;slit source&amp;nbsp;reflects&amp;nbsp;from a glass surface at
a small angle.&amp;nbsp;The reflected light then interferes with the direct light
from the source, forming&amp;nbsp;interference&amp;nbsp;fringes. This pattern is called
Lloyd's mirror effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the classical experiment light is used but the same result can be
obtained using sound waves. When a sound wave is reflected from a
surface the reflected sound wave will also interfere with the direct
sound wave. This phenomenon can also be experienced with aircraft noise
due to the ground reflection. However, because an aircraft generally
(hopefully?) moves in the sky, the interference pattern changes over the
time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I managed to include this effect in my aircraft auralisation
tool.&amp;nbsp;The figure below shows a spectrogram of a synthesized aircraft
passage. In the spectrogram the Doppler shift can be seen as well as
many curves which represent interference fringes, the Lloyd's mirror
effect. The mirror effect is in this case solely due to the ground. Now,
since my implementation supports reflections from buildings as well, the
effect will also be obtained due to these reflections from facades,
although far less pronounced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure align-center"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="https://fridh.nl/images/2013/11/mirror_effect.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://fridh.nl/images/2013/11/mirror_effect-300x226.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Spectrogram of a synthesized aircraft passage showing the Doppler effect and Lloyd's mirror effect. The x-axis shows time and y-axis frequency. The color indicates sound pressure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2013 18:12:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2013-11-15:/2013/11/15/lloyds-mirror-effect/</guid><category>acoustics</category><category>sonorus</category></item><item><title>Project meeting of SONORUS in Ghent, Belgium</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2013/11/10/project-meeting-of-sonorus-in-ghent-belgium/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Last week was the first winterschool of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.fp7sonorus.eu/"&gt;SONORUS project&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;as well
as a Network Meeting and this was also the first time for us, ESR's, to
meet each other and all other partners involved in this project. SONORUS
is an Initial Training Network under the FP7 People Programme in the
field of Urban Sound Planning, aiming at improving the acoustic
environment of our cities in a holistic approach. In the project, 14
young researchers (ESR's) work together on improving the soundscape of
several cities in conjunction with their individual research projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Sunday evening prior to the winterschool there was a dinner for all
those involved in the project, a very pleasant way to get to know each
other. On Monday morning the Network Meeting began. An introduction to
the project was given by the project leader and the research partners
also presented themselves. Juergen Bauer of WIT then gave a talk named
'Urban sound planning in the bigger context' stressing the importance of
Urban Sound Planning. That afternoon the ESR's presented themselves as
well as the involved city partners showing their cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuesday morning the winterschool truly began. From then on every day was
packed with lectures and workshops. The winterschool dealt with urban
sound propagation and therefore sound propagation and modelling
technique were extensively discussed along with standard methods and the
European Noise Directive. The winterschool was concluded on Friday with
a small exam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A topic that briefly passed by during a presentation of Timothy van
Renterghem seemed to have impressed me quite a bit. He briefly showed
the results from his research on the importance of rooftops for road
traffic noise shielding. Basically, the shape of a rooftop can have
great influence on how much sound is diffracted and thus how quiet a
courtyard could potentially become.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure align-center"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="https://fridh.nl/images/2013/11/rooftops.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://fridh.nl/images/2013/11/rooftops-300x230.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The importance of roof shape for road traffic
noise shielding in the urban environment environment, T. Van Renterghem
et al., Journal of Sound and Vibration, 2010.[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Tuesday afternoon we had an initial look together at the test cases
and groups were formed to see how they would tackle the problems that
were presented. Each group discussed a single test site and concluded
the session with a presentation about their initial impressions of the
challenge at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right from the start of this week project members started discussing
their work and how they might cooperate. Thursday after the lectures I
gave a short presentation on tools for collaboration resulting in a
brief discussion on the topic. While we were all too tired to go into
the details at the time my general impression was that the&amp;nbsp;consensus&amp;nbsp;was
that we should definitely look deeper into these kind of tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all I think this meeting was quite fruitful and I'm looking
forward to the next time!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2013 22:04:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2013-11-10:/2013/11/10/project-meeting-of-sonorus-in-ghent-belgium/</guid><category>acoustics</category><category>sonorus</category></item><item><title>Auralisation of aircraft noise</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2013/09/26/auralisation-of-aircraft-noise/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Almost two months ago I started working at the Swiss research institute
Empa in Dübendorf, Switzerland, as part of a European Seventh Framework
project called &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.fp7sonorus.eu/"&gt;Sonorus&lt;/a&gt;. The project is about urban sound planning and
my task is to develop an aircraft noise simulator. &amp;nbsp;The first two months
passed really fast. It's a great place to work, and the type of work
really fits me. Obviously I began with reading a bit about the topic and
thinking how I would tackle the issues at hand. But very soon I began
with implementing the first bits and mainly prototyping what I think it
should become.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea is that I develop an aircraft noise simulator capable of
simulating how an aircraft pass-by sounds at a stationary receiver while
in an urban environment. This means effects like spherical spreading,
Doppler shift and reflections at the ground and facades have to be
included in the propagation model. But first it is important to obtain a
good time-frequency representation of an aircraft, and obviously these
depend on the make or type of the aircraft as well as the conditions.
Finally, the aircraft noise has to be reproduced using for example an
Ambisonics setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, there are quite some challenges here and 'unknowns' to be solved .
While I have a good idea of how I will build such a tool for
auralisation, there are many details requiring attention. An example is
how much does turbulence in the atmosphere influence the propagation?
How to simulate decorrelation? How to reproduce correct over-head
information? And quite some more questions that need answering the
coming three years :-)&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2013 22:59:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2013-09-26:/2013/09/26/auralisation-of-aircraft-noise/</guid><category>acoustics</category><category>sonorus</category></item><item><title>Final weeks in India</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2013/06/29/final-weeks-in-india/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It's four weeks now that I am back in Sweden. June the 2nd I arrived
back home in Gothenburg. It was quite a change, for sure! But it was
definitely good. I really enjoyed my 4.5 months India experience, but
after some time I was starting to feel like being home again. Let's give
a short summary of the last month or so in India.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spend almost a month in McLeodGanj, a town a liked and disliked. There
are so many foreign tourists, that you don't have the feeling you're in
India. And this is both a positive and negative thing I found. Anyway,
during my stay there I met again several travelers from before which was
very nice! It's good to see some familiar faces once in a while. After
McLeodGanj - including a night at the Snowline Cafe - I headed to
Srinagar, Kashmir. It was quite a long bus journey; first a 5 hour ride
from Dharamsala to Jammu, and after that a night bus from Jammu to
Srinagar. While the ride was supposed to take about 12 hours it took in
fact 16 due to two punctures, and a driver deciding to sleep it off
instead. Unfortunately for him the police didn't agree with him and put
him to work. The ride turned out to be really nice, with amazing views
and nice discussions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Srinagar I spend only a couple of days. Somehow the city didn't
appeal to me. I think it was because it is way too touristic without
offering me any reasons to stay. So, after Srinagar I took the amazing
two-day bus ride to Leh, Ladakh! Amazing views, and nice dangerous small
roads. Awesome road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ladakh is beautiful. Certain locations are simply stunning. It is a pity
though that all the valleys are full of military bases. This does
destroy some of the immersion. It's also unfortunate that Leh has been
growing so much; big concrete hotels are appearing everywhere and they
simply don't fit in. Since I had quite some work left on my thesis I
wasn't able to explore much of Ladakh but I will definitely come back
here for trekking, or maybe some teaching? We'll see!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 29 Jun 2013 13:42:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2013-06-29:/2013/06/29/final-weeks-in-india/</guid><category>india</category><category>study</category></item><item><title>Holi and McLeod Ganj</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2013/04/25/holi-and-mcleod-ganj/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In my previous post I wrote how few foreign tourists could be found in
Shimla. Well, I've spend some weeks now here in McLeod Ganj, and I &amp;nbsp;can
tell you it's quite the opposite. You really have to look hard to find
Indian people around here! Okay, they're still here, but seem to be a
minority compared to the huge amounts of Tibetan people and foreign
tourists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, let's continue where I finished last time. I spend quite some
time in Shimla, and during my stay I met again some travelers I met
before in Udaipur and Jodhpur, which was quite nice. Unlike me they have
been to many more places since we split ways so it was very nice to
catch up and hear their stories of their travels. It was actually the
last day for me in Shimla when I met two Canadians I had met before in
Jodhpur. While they decided to spend Holi in Shimla I went back to
Delhi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So....Delhi and Holi. Quite some people are afraid of this combination,
but I must say there is no reason at all. While it can get chaotic
(drunk rickshaw drivers doing tricks on their rickshaws, waterballoons
coming at you from all directions), it is a VERY nice and colourful day!
I had a great day and stay there and look forward to a next Holi :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some days after Holi I took the bus again, and this time to Dharamsala
or more precise, McLeod Ganj. McLeod Ganj is the area where the Tibetan
government in exile can be found and as such many Tibetan refugees live
here. Many foreigners could also be found due to popularity of the Dalai
Lama and Tibetan&amp;nbsp;Buddhism. While I am one of the foreigners here I must
say I am definitely not here for this reason. Most foreigners that I met
here in McLeod Ganj come to learn about that culture, for meditation or
to smoke.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again I met some travelers from before here, which was nice to spend
some time with again. By now though they've all left, and so I feel it's
time to move on again as well. As I've been working real hard on my
thesis again for a while (except last week due to a stupid injury) I
feel like having a short break again. Therefore my plan is to go to
Dalhousie for a dat or two, departing at the end of the weekend. After
that I continue my plans by heading to Srinagar. I haven't figured out
yet whether I go there via Udhampur or Jammu. While I don't want to go
via the latter I am told it is easiest to go from there. Hmmm, I'll have
to think about it. Maybe when I go up Triund again and spend the night
at the Snowline Cafe?&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2013 12:46:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2013-04-25:/2013/04/25/holi-and-mcleod-ganj/</guid><category>india</category></item><item><title>Jodhpur!</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2013/02/14/jodhpur/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;During my previous post I already wrote that I arrived in Jodhpur, how
amazing the guesthouse was and that I went to see an Indian doctor. The
medication did its work and after some days I was feeling good again,
and ready to explore the town!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure align-center"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="https://fridh.nl/images/2013/02/IMG_0169-1024x768.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://fridh.nl/images/2013/02/IMG_0169-300x225.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The fortress&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jodhpur has a nice bazaar around the clocktower. Here one can also find
excellent lassis which are actually quite a bit different from the other
lassies I had so far. A lassi is a drink that consists of yogurt mixed
with water and spices. Normally one drinks a lassi but this one is quite
a bit thicker, requiring the use of a spoon. It also had a strong lemon
taste to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure align-center"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="https://fridh.nl/images/2013/02/IMG_0188-1024x768.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://fridh.nl/images/2013/02/IMG_0188-300x225.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The fortress entrance&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main attraction of Jodhpur is the fortress. Located on a hill it is
beautiful to see. The fortress also offers amazing views over the new
and the old, blue city. In this case I think pictures say more than
words :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure align-center"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="https://fridh.nl/images/2013/02/IMG_0259-1024x768.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://fridh.nl/images/2013/02/IMG_0259-300x225.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Room&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure align-center"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="https://fridh.nl/images/2013/02/IMG_0241-1024x768.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://fridh.nl/images/2013/02/IMG_0241-300x225.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The blue city and a flock of pigeons that can always be found at the fort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2013 06:04:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2013-02-14:/2013/02/14/jodhpur/</guid><category>india</category></item><item><title>Agra, Jaipur and now Jodhpur</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2013/02/02/agra-jaipur-and-now-jodhpur/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Two and a half weeks ago I arrived in Delhi. Since then I went to Agra,
Jaipur, and Jodhpur, where I decided to stay some longer. Let's try and
keep it chronological, and start with Agra.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Taj Mahal" src="https://fridh.nl/images/2013/02/IMG_0128-300x225.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was in Agra for I think 5 nights, and the location I was staying, Saj
Palace, was quite nice. There were plenty small restaurants and shops
around, and the hotel had a nice view on the Taj. People came and went,
but like me, there was a Canadian family staying a bit longer. They were
actually on a world trip of a whopping 14 months! Anyhow, in Agra I
finally was able to do some work on my thesis as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Agra Fort" src="https://fridh.nl/images/2013/02/IMG_0130-300x225.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Agra I went by train to Jaipur during which I had a nice
conversation with a local. She was having a puppy along, and, as long as
the other people in the coach wouldn't mind, according to the rules the
dog should be allowed to stay. Well, I was the only other one, and I
didn't mind at all, but somehow the conductor didn't agree and sent the
dog to a special coach. So stupid...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, Jaipur. I don't have much positive to say about my stay there.
While the hotel had friendly personnel and the rooms were quite good, it
was so damn noisy I couldn't get any sleep at all. And when you then get
diarrhea as well...pfff. But before I got that I did get to see some of
the town, but there wasn't anything special in my opinion, and therefore
I wouldn't recommend anyone to go there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Old city of Jaipur" src="https://fridh.nl/images/2013/02/IMG_0156-300x225.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of the diarrhea and fever I stayed a bit longer in Jaipur.
Eventually I decided to go to Jodhpur even though I was still sick. The
train ride from Jaipur to Jodhpur was I think the best moment I've had
during my stay here. I booked a ticket for an AC3 coach, but wasn't able
to find it as all the numbers were messed up when it arrived. I went
instead in a normal sleeper class. The smell at first was horrible, but
after a few minutes you're used to it. I put my stuff away,  lay down on
a berth, in the sun shine, with the windows open the wind going through
the coach. It was great! In the meanwhile, cracking some nuts and
talking to some locals. Best moment so far :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Jodhpor I am now staying at a great hotel. The people that are
working here are very friendly, the food is the best I had thus far, and
it's quiet! Like me there are quite some others here who are traveling
for more than four months through India. Some are going from north to
south, while others went south first. It's interesting to hear where
they've been, and what they thought of the places, as I also haven't
decided where I will be going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two days ago I went to see a doctor and got some medication for the
diarrhea and fever. I think I got it because I drank half a glass of tap
water. Stupid. Things seem to be improving now, though the antibiotics
are making me so tired, that I haven't been able to explore Jodhpur yet.
As I will be staying for a least another 5 days in Jodhpur, that
shouldn't be a problem though. After those five days I will take the
train to Jaisalmer where I would like to go on a 2 or 3 day camel
safari.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2013 08:09:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2013-02-02:/2013/02/02/agra-jaipur-and-now-jodhpur/</guid><category>india</category></item><item><title>Summer in Norway</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2012/07/21/summer-in-norway/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Many that know me are aware of the fact that I am spending this summer
in Oslo, Norway. In May I was offered a position for the summer at the
Noise &amp;amp; Vibration section at &lt;a href="http://www.dnv.com/"&gt;Det Norske Veritas&lt;/a&gt; in Høvik. Thus far I
am quite content with the work. I've been traveling a lot across Norway
for noise and vibration measurements (DNV Comfort Class) and I've
started working on noise and vibration predictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oslo seems to be a nice city as well. Especially the location where I
live; everything is basically around the corner. Commuting time is
acceptable and nature can be reached in about half an hour.
Unfortunately I haven't really been able to see much of the nature
outside Oslo due to the bad weather and a bad fever last week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coming week I am having off from work, and what way to spend it
better than to go hiking! Monday I will take the bus/train to Liomseter
from where I will hike for five days along the final part of
Jotunheimstien. Last week I bought all the gear (ouch, Gore-Tex is
expensive!!) I think I will need for this and future trips. What future
trips, you might ask. Well, at least end of next month I intend to walk
the &lt;a href="Kungsleden: http://www.svenskaturistforeningen.se/en/Discover-Sweden/Facilities-and-activities/Lappland/kingstrail/"&gt;Kungsleden&lt;/a&gt; in Sweden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, summer thus far has been quite nice with visiting The
Netherlands again, as well as attending &lt;a href="http://www.hultsfredsfestivalen.se/"&gt;Hultsfredsfestivalen&lt;/a&gt; in
Sweden. And with the forecast of the hiking trips it only seems to
become better :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To end this post I have here a nice recording of the Norwegian band
Katzenjammer, who were playing at Hultsfredsfestivalen as well, though
this is a recording from elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="390"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/hHcklZEi1kk'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 21 Jul 2012 21:50:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2012-07-21:/2012/07/21/summer-in-norway/</guid><category>acoustics</category><category>norway</category><category>sweden</category><category>work</category></item><item><title>Article about my 2009 internship project</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2010/07/07/article-about-my-2009-internship-project/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In 2009 I had an internship in DGMR and developed an acoustic measuring
system, as I described a bit &lt;a href="http://fridh.nl/projects/autonomic-acoustical-measuring-instrument/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. After my internship I continued
working on this project. Now an article has appeared about it in
'Technisch Weekblad' and at their &lt;a href="http://www.technischweekblad.nl/special-topproject-dgmr-meet-geluid-met-onbemande.91122.lynkx"&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2010 09:05:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2010-07-07:/2010/07/07/article-about-my-2009-internship-project/</guid><category>school</category><category>study</category><category>work</category></item><item><title>The '59 sound</title><link>https://fridh.nl/2009/12/20/the-59-sound/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                &lt;iframe width="640" height="390"
                    src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/bOBb13yDnzo'
                    frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen
                    allowFullScreen&gt;
                &lt;/iframe&gt;
            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Frederik Rietdijk</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2009 16:49:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:fridh.nl,2009-12-20:/2009/12/20/the-59-sound/</guid><category>music</category></item></channel></rss>