<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>FRidh's blog - norway</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/tag/norway.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2012-07-21T21:50:00+02:00</updated><subtitle>Discovery consists of seeing what everybody has seen and thinking what nobody has thought -- Albert Szent-Gyorgyi</subtitle><entry><title>Summer in Norway</title><link href="/2012/07/21/summer-in-norway/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-07-21T21:50:00+02:00</published><updated>2012-07-21T21:50:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Frederik Rietdijk</name></author><id>tag:None,2012-07-21:/2012/07/21/summer-in-norway/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Many that know me are aware of the fact that I am spending this summer
in Oslo, Norway. In May I was offered a position for the summer at the
Noise &amp;amp; Vibration section at &lt;a href="http://www.dnv.com/"&gt;Det Norske Veritas&lt;/a&gt; in Høvik. Thus far I
am quite content with the work. I've been traveling a lot across Norway
for noise and vibration measurements (DNV Comfort Class) and I've
started working on noise and vibration predictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oslo seems to be a nice city as well. Especially the location where I
live; everything is basically around the corner. Commuting time is
acceptable and nature can be reached in about half an hour.
Unfortunately I haven't really been able to see much of the nature
outside Oslo due to the bad weather and a bad fever last week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coming week I am having off from work, and what way to spend it
better than to go hiking! Monday I will take the bus/train to Liomseter
from where I will hike for five days along the final part of
Jotunheimstien. Last week I bought all the gear (ouch, Gore-Tex is
expensive!!) I think I will need for this and future trips. What future
trips, you might ask. Well, at least end of next month I intend to walk
the &lt;a href="Kungsleden: http://www.svenskaturistforeningen.se/en/Discover-Sweden/Facilities-and-activities/Lappland/kingstrail/"&gt;Kungsleden&lt;/a&gt; in Sweden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, summer thus far has been quite nice with visiting The
Netherlands again, as well as attending &lt;a href="http://www.hultsfredsfestivalen.se/"&gt;Hultsfredsfestivalen&lt;/a&gt; in
Sweden. And with the forecast of the hiking trips it only seems to
become better :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To end this post I have here a nice recording of the Norwegian band
Katzenjammer, who were playing at Hultsfredsfestivalen as well, though
this is a recording from elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                    &lt;iframe width="640" height="390"
                        src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/hHcklZEi1kk'
                        frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen
                        mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen&gt;
                    &lt;/iframe&gt;
                &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog"></category><category term="acoustics"></category><category term="norway"></category><category term="sweden"></category><category term="work"></category></entry></feed>